Guide to the Cassirer collection, 1906-1933
Department of Special Collections
Cassirer collection,
1906-1933
Special Collections M0287
Cassirer, Bruno.; Cassirer, Paul, 1871-1926.
.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
l. Bruno Cassirer Verlag papers, gifts of George Hill, 1979, 1980, and Peter Paret, 1986. 2. Paul Cassirer Verlag papers and Paul Cassirer papers, gifts of Peter Paret, 1978, 1979, 1980, 1983, 1985, and 1986.
Biographical Note
Bruno (1872-1941) and Paul (1871-1926) Cassirer were cousins who in 1898 opened an art gallery closely associated with the Berlin Secession. Their opening exhibition featured works of Degas, Meunier, and Liebermann. Later shows included Corinth, Slevogt, Hodler, Bocklin, and Trubner; the emphasis, however, was on French impressionists. Soon after opening their gallery, the Cassirers began publishing. Their ties to Max Liebermann are close; their first publications were a set of prints by Liebermann and his essay on Degas.
In 1901, the cousins parted company. Paul Cassirer continued as art dealer, and Bruno took over as publisher; they agreed not to compete directly for a period of seven years. In 1902 Bruno Cassirer began publishing the journal Kunst and Künstler, which soon enjoyed success and influence. In the field of art and art history, he published Wilhelm von Bode, Alfred Lichtwark, Hugo v. Tschudi, Karl Scheffler, and many others. Bruno Cassirer also published in the fields of philosophy and literature. The lector for literature was Christian Morgenstern, who also served as editor of Das Theater, founded in 1903, and attracted among others, Julius Bab, Alfred Kerr, and Hugo v. Hofmannsthal to the journal. Bruno Cassirer also published fine quality, limited edition, illustrated books. Slevogt and Walser were among Cassirer's top illustrators. In 1908, when the cousins' agreement not to compete ended, Bruno Cassirer began publishing graphic art.
First the war and the inflation, finally the Nazis' rise to power (many of Cassirer's authors and artists were unofficially banned, and Cassirer himself was Jewish) hurt the publishing house. Bruno Cassirer left for England in 1938 to rebuild the house there. He died in 1941. His son-in-law Dr. George Hill continues the work of Bruno Cassirer (Publishers) Ltd.
If Bruno can be called the book Cassirer, Paul was the art Cassirer. In 1901, when the cousins parted company, Paul Cassirer took over the art gallery and strengthened his connections with the Berlin Secession, of which he was the business manager (since 1898). Paul Cassirer's gallery established itself as the center for the new modern art in Berlin, with exhibits of artists of the Berlin Secession, of French impressionists, and of van Gogh. As Cassirer attempted to strengthen his control over the Berlin Secession power struggles developed within the group. In 1910 he was asked to take a six-month leave, however he eventually became president of the group (1912-1915).
After 1908, Paul Cassirer undertook a number of projects in competition with his cousin. He first established the Pan-Presse to publish fine illustrated books and original graphic art; the first effort of the press was the Leatherstocking Tales, illustrated by Slevogt. In 1910 he established the literary/art journal Pan, which included Alfred Kerr among its editors. Among the contributors to Pan were Frank Wedekind, Georg Heym, Ernst Barlach, and Franz Marc. Connected with the journal was a society by the same name which sponsored theater productions for invited audiences of drama forbidden by the censor for public performance.
In 1914 at the beginning of the war, Paul Cassirer began publishing Kriegszeit, Künstler-Flugblätter, edited by Alfred Gold. The early illustrations and texts were patriotic and full of war fervor. Paul Cassirer volunteered for the army in July 1914, but returned in 1916 as an enemy of the war. By this time Kriegszeit had been discontinued; Leo Kestenberg was editing the new journal Der Bildermann, devoted to art rather than patriotism. During the remaining war years, Cassirer and his wife, actress Tilla Durieux, became increasingly active politically. Cassirer, an independent Social Democrat (USPD), established in 1918 the Bund neues Vaterland, a club that sponsored discussions with journalists and politicians.
Paul Cassirer's publishing house enjoyred prestige and success not only in the fields of art and art history, but also in politics and literature. Cassirer published works by Eduard Bernstein, Rosa Luxemburg, Erich Mühsam, Ernst Toller, Toller, Ernst Barlach, Ludwig Meidner, and Walter Hasenclever, and René Schuckele. Paul Cassirer committed suicide on January 7, 1926.
Further reading: For further information on the Bruno Cassirer and Paul Cassirer Publishing Houses consult the following articles that appeared in a special issue of the political Imprimatur in 1972: (copies available in the collection file upon request)
Scope and Content
Papers of the publishing houses of Bruno and Paul Cassirer, and manuscripts by Paul Cassirer. I. Papers of the Bruno Cassirer publishing house (1906-1933) include the original verdict of the Koniglich Preussisches Landgenicht Berlin in the 1906 obscenity case against Bruno Cassirer and Frank Wedekind, regarding Wedekind's "Die Buchse der Pandora." There is also a catalogue, "Einige neuere Erscheinungen aus dem Verlage Bruno Cassirer, Berlin, nd. II. Papers of the Paul Cassirer publishing house (1916-1919) include ca. 100 letters of correspondence between Paul Cassirer, Leo Kestenberg (Cassirer employee), Walter Hasenclever (author), and Fritz Newberger (agent for O. Kokoschka and Hasenclever), mostly concerning the performance of Hasenclever's play, "Der Sohn" and Kokoschka's paintings; also includes manuscripts by Eduard Bernstein, Hasenclever and Peter Meyer, and letters to the editor of the journal "Pan," published by Cassirer. III. The Paul Cassirer manuscripts (1890-1899 and n.d.) include plays, short stories, poems, and fragments. In addition there are two photographs of Stefan Anton George, n.d., and one publisher's announcement for a work by Friedrich Gundolf, 1932.
Series Description
- I. Papers (1906-1933)of the Bruno Cassirer publishing house including the original verdict of the Königlich Preussisches Landgericht Berlin in the 1906 obscenity case against Bruno Cassirer and Frank Wedekind, regarding Wedekind's Die Büchse der Pandora.
- II. Papers (1916-1919)of the Paul Cassirer publishing house including ca. one hundred letters of correspondence between Paul Cassirer, Leo Kestenberg (Cassirer employee), Walter Hasenclever (author), and Fritz Neuberger (agent for O. Kokoschka and Hasenclever) mostly concerning the performance of Hasenclever's play Der Sohn and Kokoschka's paintings; also includes manuscripts by Eduard Bernstein, Hasenclever and Peter Meyer, and letters to the editor of the journal Pan, published by Cassirer.
- III. Paul Cassirer papers: manuscripts for plays, short stories, poems, and fragments. (1890s and n.d.)
- IV. Additions: 90.077 (85-02)
Container List
- Series I. Bruno Cassirer Verlag Papers (1906-1933)
  - Preußisches Landgericht II, Berlin. (Folder 1)
  - March 9, 1906.Court decision re: Frank Wedekind's Die Büchse der Pandora. (Gift of George Hill, 1979)., TD, 53 pp.
  - Mendelsohn, Franz V. (Folder 2)
  - June 21, 1924.To Fritz Cassirer re: death of Julius Cassirer. (Gift of George Hill, 1980)., TLS, 1 p.
  - Grosz, George (1893-1959)and Eva. (Folder 3)
  - (Dec. 1932).To [Bruno] Cassirer. (Gift of George Hill, 1978)., ALS, 1 p.
  - Hesse, Hermann (1877-1962). (Folder 4a)
  - Nov. 20, 1933,To Bruno Cassirer. Poem Besinnung. (Gift of George Hill, 1978)., TMsS (carbon), 1 p.
  - 2 Bruno Cassirer Verlag catalogs, 1936 [UNK] (Folder 4b)
- Series II. Paul Cassirer Verlag Papers (1916-1919)
  - A. Cassirer-Kestenberg-Hasenclever-Neuberger Correspondence
    - Hasenclever, Walter (1890-1940) (Folder 5)
      - Jan. 26, 1917.To Leo Kestenberg., ALS, 3pp.
      - May 24, 1917.To Leo Kestenberg., ALS, 1p.
      - June 25, 1917.To Leo Kestenberg. (Gift of Peter Paret, 1979)., ALS, 2pp.
    - Cassirer, Paul (1871-1926) (Folder 6)
      - July 27, 1917.To Walter Hasenclever., TL (carbon), 5pp.
      - July 30, 1917.To Fritz Neuberger., TL (carbon), 2pp.
      - n.d.,To (theater director). (Gift of Peter Paret, 1979)., TL (pencil corrections, revisions), 1p.
    - Kestenberg, Leo (Folder 7)
      - May 3, 1917-March 20, 1918.To Fritz Neuberger. (Gift of Peter Paret, 1979)., 24 TL (carbon); 27 leaves
    - Neuberger, Fritz (Folder 8)
      - July 27, 1917.To Paul Cassirer., ALS, 2pp.
      - Jan. 27, 1918.To Paul Cassirer. (Gift of Peter Paret, 1979)., TLS, 1p.
    - Neuberger, Fritz (Folder 9)
      - Nov. 14, 1916-June 29, 1917.To Leo Kestenberg. (Gift of Peter Paret, 1979), 38 ALS, 2 ACS, and 4 TL; 50 leaves
    - Neuberger, Fritz (Folder 10)
      - July 1, 1917-March 21, 1919.To Leo Kestenberg. (Gift of Peter Paret, 1979), 20 ALS, 7 TLS, 9 ACS, 1 TCS, and 3 TL; 52 leaves
    - Pan. (Journal published by Paul Cassirer Verlag). Incoming Correspondence: 1910-1911., 8 letters (Folder 11)
  - B. Manuscripts of Authors of the Paul Cassirer Verlag
    - Bernstein, Eduard (1850-1932) (Folder 12)
      - Aug. 22, 1919.Forward to the works of Ferdinand Lassalle, published by Paul Cassirer, 1919. (Gift of Peter Paret, 1979)., AMsS, 3pp.
    - Hasenclever, Walter (1890-1940) (Folder 13)
      - Autumn 1917. Tod und Reichstag. Ein Flugblatt. Original manuscript with corrections, revisions; sent to Leo Kestenberg Nov. 4, 1917., AMsS, 38pp.
      - n.d. Gottes Hand in Lowen., TMs (carbon), 2pp.
      - n.d. Der politische Dichter. (Gift of Peter Paret, 1979)., TMs (carbon), 3pp.
    - Meyer, Peter (Folder 14)
      - n.d. Über die Form. (Gift of Peter Paret, 1979)., TMsS (carbon), 78pp. (missing p. 1)
- Series III. Paul Cassirer Papers
  - A. Manuscripts
    - Manuscript of the Novel Josef Geiger, incomplete, (Gift of Peter Paret, 1983)., 75pp. (Folder 15)
      The published version of this manuscript is available in Folder 20 of this collection.
    - Manuscript of the Comedy Der gelbe Frack, two versions, (Gift of Peter Paret, 1983)., 35pp. (Folder 16)
    - Manuscripts of short stories, plays, poems: (Gift of Peter Paret, 1983):, (10 items) (Folder 17)
      - Der Anstoß, 7 pages
      - Eine Lüge, 4 1/2 pages
      - In der Nacht, 4 1/2 pages
      - Verheiratet, 30 pages
      - Der kleine Engel, 7 pages
      - Das Versprechen, 14 pages (2 versions)
      - Herr Frühling, 1 page
      - Nocturno, 6 pages (and other stories)
      - Chapter 4, 9 pages (of untitled novel)
      - Fragments, 11 pages
    - Manuscripts of Plays (Gift of Peter Paret, 1986), (4 items) (Folder 18)
      - Schlaf, Kindchen, Schlaf (1894), 9p.
      - Der kleine Engel, (different version), 7p.
      - Fragment, n.d., pp. 243-262 (19p.)
      - Fragment, n.d., p. 24 (1p.)
  - B. Books
    - Paul Cassirer, Fritz Reiner, der Maler (Dresden and Leipzig, 1894),(Gift of Peter Paret, 1983)., xerox copy. (Folder 19)
    - Paul Kahrs (=Paul Cassirer), Josef Geiger (Leipzig, 1895),(Gift of Peter Paret, 1983)., xerox copy and 2 proof title pages. (Folder 20)
      The manuscript version of this book is available in Folder 15 of this collection.
- Series IV. Additions:
  - Stefan Searge: n.d., 90.077; 2 photos
  - Fredrich Gundolf: 1 publishers announcement, 1932.
  - Envel in searge's hand to Gundolf
Bibliography
Löhneysen, Wolfgang Freiherr v. Paul Cassirer-Beschreibung eines Phänomens. Imprimatur, NF7, 1972, pp. 153-180.
Sarkowski, Heinz. Bruno Cassirer. Ein deutscher Verlag 1898-1938. Imprimatur, NF7, 1972, pp. 107-131.
Sarkowski, Heinz. Bruno Cassirer - Zeugnisse der Zeitgenossen. Imprimatur, NF7, 1972, pp. 132-138.
Scheffler, Karl. Bruno Cassirer und das illustrierte Buch. Imprimatur, NF7, 1972, pp. 139-142.
Sichowsky, Anke v. and Gunter Steinbach. Kinder- und Jugendbücher im Bruno Cassirer Verlag. Imprimatur, NF7, 1972, pp. 143-152.
H.K. Lempertz-Auktion: Tilla Durieux' Nachlass. Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung. June 26, 1982. p. 28.